<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Python on  </title>
    <link>https://chriswayg.github.io/tags/python/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Ant Zucaro</author>
    <rights>Copyright (c) 2009 - 2014, Ant Zucaro; all rights reserved.</rights>
    <updated>2014-05-16 09:55:00 -0500 -0500</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unicode Characters</title>
      <link>https://chriswayg.github.io/posts/2014/unicode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 09:55:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Ant Zucaro</author>
      <guid>https://chriswayg.github.io/posts/2014/unicode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The other day I was adding support for some unicode characters within &lt;a href=&#34;http://stats.xonotic.org&#34;&gt;XonStat&lt;/a&gt; and during the process stumbled upon a few helpful things. It turns out that many Linux applications provide for the easy entry of code point values with a simple key press combination: while holding the control and shift keys, enter &amp;lsquo;U&amp;rsquo; and then the unicode code point value to insert that character into whatever text buffer you&amp;rsquo;re currently working with. For example, entering the character &amp;ldquo;é&amp;rdquo; (at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Unicode/Character_reference/0000-0FFF&#34;&gt;code point&lt;/a&gt; 00E9) you would hold control and shift and then enter U, 0, 0, E, 9. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s even better is that Firefox is one of the apps that supports this entry method. This is especially useful for playing around with your @font-face declarations, since entry behaves the same way within the developer tools as well. That meant that instead of searching for a Xonotic player who had a special character in their nick (which is what I was testing), I could simply inspect their nickname and insert an arbitrary code point to see if it displayed the font&amp;rsquo;s glyph properly. Similarly, I could also specify any code point in a POST request for incoming data by doing the same thing if needed (at the time I didn&amp;rsquo;t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unfortunate thing is that many text editors have had the same functionality for a long time, and each has developed their own entry pattern. Entering these characters in Vim, for example, requires hitting Control-V while in insert mode, then entering U and the code point value. This isn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all, it&amp;rsquo;s just slightly different from how other applications handle it. I guess you can&amp;rsquo;t have it all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my testing process I also found out that Python 2 has several flavors of unicode literals developers can use. I was naively assuming that all code points could be entered with one syntax, so I was assembling four and five hex-character code points with the same format: \uXXXXX, with the Xs being the code point value in hexadecimal. My @font-face had its glyphs mostly in the four character range, but it did have a few in the five character range. It was those that weren&amp;rsquo;t working properly, which caused me endless frustration. I was entering &amp;ldquo;\u1F680&amp;rdquo; as the code point literal in the code, but I kept getting an omega symbol (U+1F68) and a 0 on my display! I kept scratching my head over this until I looked closely into the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.python.org/2/howto/unicode.html#unicode-literals-in-python-source-code&#34;&gt;Python documentation&lt;/a&gt;. I soon found out that there is a separate syntax for code points above the four character range: \UXXXXXXXX. The fix in my code was to change all of the five-character code points to have an upper-case U and to pad them such that they contained 8 hexadecimal characters in total. You can see a few examples of this change in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/antzucaro/XonStat/blob/master/xonstat/util.py#L58&#34;&gt;this line of code&lt;/a&gt;. After making this change all of the glyphs in the font worked perfectly. Phew!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
