<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>life on Hugo Future Imperfect</title>
    <link>/liawagner.github.io/categories/life/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in life on Hugo Future Imperfect</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/liawagner.github.io/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Greater is he</title>
      <link>/liawagner.github.io/blog/greater-is-he/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 11:53:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/liawagner.github.io/blog/greater-is-he/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The king rejoices in your strength, Yahweh! How greatly he rejoices in your salvation! You have given him his heart&amp;rsquo;s desire, and have not withheld the request of his lips. For you meet him with the blessings of goodness. You set a crown of fine gold on his head. He asked life of you, you gave it to him, even length of days forever and ever. His glory is great in your salvation. You lay honor and majesty on him. For you make him most blessed forever. You make him glad with joy in your presence. For the king trusts in Yahweh. Through the loving kindness of the Most High, he shall not be moved. Your hand will find out all of your enemies. Your right hand will find out those who hate you. You will make them as a fiery furnace in the time of your anger. Yahweh will swallow them up in his wrath. The fire shall devour them. You will destroy their descendants from the earth, their posterity from among the children of men. For they intended evil against you. They plotted evil against you which cannot succeed. For you will make them turn their back, when you aim drawn bows at their face. Be exalted, Yahweh, in your strength, so we will sing and praise your power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../uploads/2017/02/10/Site%20Banner%20-%20Child%20-%201900px.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LORD, you have been our dwelling place for all generations. Before the mountains were brought forth, before you had formed the earth and the world, even from everlasting to everlasting, you are God. You turn man to destruction, saying, «Return, you children of men.» For a thousand years in your sight are just like yesterday when it is past, like a watch in the night. You sweep them away as they sleep. In the morning they sprout like new grass. In the morning it sprouts and springs up. By evening, it is withered and dry. For we are consumed in your anger. We are troubled in your wrath. You have set our iniquities before you, our secret sins in the light of your presence. For all our days have passed away in your wrath. We bring our years to an end as a sigh. The days of our years are seventy, or even by reason of strength eighty years; yet their pride is but labor and sorrow, for it passes quickly, and we fly away. Who knows the power of your anger, your wrath according to the fear that is due to you? So teach us to number our days, that we may gain a heart of wisdom. Relent, Yahweh! How long? Have compassion on your servants! Satisfy us in the morning with your loving kindness, that we may rejoice and be glad all our days. Make us glad for as many days as you have afflicted us, for as many years as we have seen evil. Let your work appear to your servants; your glory to their children. Let the favor of the LORD our God be on us; establish the work of our hands for us; yes, establish the work of our hands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>